# Usman Magbool Bhutta

Robotics Institute, CYT Building, HKUST, Clear Water Bay, HK

□ (+852) 609-44-786 | wsmanmaqbool@outlook.com | # usmanmaqbool.github.io | □ UsmanMaqbool | □ usmanmaqbool

"Be so good they can't ignore you."

### **Summary**

This is M Usman Maqbool Bhutta. I'm PhD candidate at (Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab) HKUST. My PhD primary research is on multi-agent SLAM system and the expected graduation (~ Mar. 2021). I developed multi-agent direct SLAM systems triggered by first loop-closure matching (see my publication section). Furthermore, I'm currently working for a better and lightweight place recognition techniques using machine learning. I'm Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises. I've 7+ years of experience specializing in robotics R&D and project management. I previously owned an IT company, and I've part of several startups since 2011. My full profile can view here (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

## **Work Experience [7+ Years]**

#### RESEARCH (COMPUTER VISION TECHNOLOGIES AND SYSTEM)

#### Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics Institute

**HKUST**. HK

PHD CANDIDATE

Sep 2016 - Present

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Research in Place Recognition In-Progress: I'm currently working for making the better place recognition for the robotic state estimation by better scene understanding compared to the relocalization technologies. This work evaluation is done on the Pittsburge and Tokyo 247 Datasets compared to NetVLAD and APANet.

Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, PIP, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

• Research in Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work got accepted in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics..

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

• Research in SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

• Research in Automation: For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, PIP, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

#### Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL)

ETH Zürich, Switzerland.

ACADEMIC GUEST

MPHIL CANDIDATE

Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, PIP, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

#### **Department of Electronics**

**OAU**, Pakistan Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.

• Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

### INDUSTRY AND ENTREPRENEURSHIP

#### **Lisee Technology Corporation Limited**

Central, HK

Jan 2018 - Present

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 May 20).
- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 May 19).

#### **Friends Corporate Technologies**

Islamabad, PK Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

#### **Federal Government of Pakistan**

**Islamabad**, PK

May 2012 - Feb 2013

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing

SCIENTIFIC OFFICER

Server4Sale, LLC Islamabad PK

PHP DEVELOPER

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

#### **ACADEMIC**

**Department of Computer Science** 

**BZU-Sahiwal**, Pakistan

Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Aug. 2015 - Apr. 2016

LECTURER (VISITING)

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

**Department of Physics GPGC** Sahiwal, Pakistan

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

**Department of Electronics QAU**, Pakistan

INSTRUCTER Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

### **Education**

#### Ph.D. Candidate in Robotics at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

**HKUST**, Hong Kong

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC & COMPUTER ENGINEERING, THE HONG KONG UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Sep. 2016 - ~Feb. 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- · Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry.

M.Phil. in Electronics **OAU**, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

- Mar. 2010 Jun. 2012 • M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- · Research: Signal and Image Processing
- · Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics **OAU**, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- 2nd position in batch
- Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

#### **B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics**

**BZU**, Pakistan

BAHAUDDIN ZAKARIYA UNIVERSITY, MULTAN PAKISTAN

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

· Grade: 1st Division

## **Presentation**

#### IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

#### Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS COO LISEE TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION COMPANY LIMITED, HONG KONG.

Jan. 2019

• Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

#### IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR • Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

CityU, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS COO LISEE TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION COMPANY LIMITED, HONG KONG.

IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS PARTICIPENT May 2018

HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

#### **High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship**

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS ENTREPRENEUR

Dec. 2017

• Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

#### **World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017**

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

PRESENTER AS AUTHOR.

Nov. 2017

• Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

## Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

#### INTERNATIONAL

July. 2018	<b>Best Student Paper Finalist Award,</b> IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and	Tianjin, China
	Intelligent Systems	riarijiri, Criiria
May, 2018	Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Nov, 2017	Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
May, 2017	Completion Award, The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Dec, 2016	Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
Nov, 2016	Completion Award, Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus	HKUST, HK

#### **DOMESTIC**

Sep 2016	<b>CCMS PhD Scholarship</b> , Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK	Lahore, PK
Sep 2013	<b>Participant</b> , Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, Case EPICA	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Oct 2012	Participant, Punjab Youth Festival	Lahore, PK
Oct 2011	Participant, Int'l Youth Conference and Festival	Islamabad, PK
Sep 2011	Participant, Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival	Lahore, PK
Apr 2011	<b>Completion Award,</b> Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2011	Participant, National Drama Festival	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2010	Instuctor of short Course, PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan	Mansehra, PK
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2008	Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU	Islamabad, PK

### **Academic Activities**

IROS	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2020
Spr 2020	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing	HKUST, HK
ICRA	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2020
Spr 2019	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing	HKUST, HK
CASE	Referee Service, IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering	2019
IROS	Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems	2019, 2018
Fall 2018	Teaching Assistant, ELEC4820 - Medical Imaging	HKUST, HK
Spr 2018	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing	HKUST, HK
Spr 2017	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> , ELEC 1010 - Electronic and Information Technology	HKUST, HK

## Research Publications \_\_\_\_\_

## **Loop-box:** Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Mapping

Journal Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta\*, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu,Ming Liu

IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF: 11+)

Conference Paper

## Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects for Industrial Automation

nerence ruper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta\*, Shoaib Aslam, Peng Yun, Jianhao JIAO, Ming Liu

Oct 2020

Oct 2020

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020)

Conference Paper

Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Wang, Ming Liu, Rui Fan

Oct 2018

Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018)

## PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM

Conference Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA\*, MING LIU

Jul 2018

Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award.

## An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm

Conference Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA\*, HASAN MAHMOOD, AND HAROON MALIK

Jul 2014

Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014).

#### **Efficient Reset Design Techniques**

Journal Paper

Qamar, Zoha, Bushra Yaseen, and Usman Maqbool

Published in Science International Lahore

2015

## Skills\_

Robotics and Computer Vision Ubuntu, ROS, Docker, Catkin, Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA

**Programming** Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX

Web Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL

Languages English, Urdu

## References\_

Prof Ming Liu Ph.D. Supervisor

Associate Professor · Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB) eelium@ust.hk

(+852) 2358 7058

#### Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma

Exchange Co-Supervisor

SENIOR RESEARCHER · ASL, ETH ZÜRICH, SWITZERLAND

cesarcadena.lerma@gmail.com

(+41) (0)44 633-8803

Prof. Hasan Mahmood M.Phil. Supervisor

Professor · Chairperson, Department of Electronics, QAU, Islamabad, Pakistan.

hasan@qau.edu.pk

(+92) (0)51 9064 3132